[music]
>> Welcome to 2026 release wave two of
Business Central. This is a long awaited
launch edition video for what's new in
MCP server. My name is Kenny
Pontoppidan. I'm a program manager in
the Business Central team and with me
I'm very proud to have my colleague Poor
Shot.
>> Everyone, my name is Poor Shot Dwivedi.
I'm a senior engineer with the runtime
team at Business Central.
>> Poor Shot's going to show some excellent
demos in a sec. But first let's see what
we have overall for you.
We're going to talk about two things, a
new tool, actually four new tools for
doing queries. And then some some nice
improvements of the user experience for
setting up MCP in Business Central.
So, the query tool in Business Central,
if I should explain it in four
sentences, it would be
have your MCP host, whatever that is,
Copilot Studio, VS Code, or other,
have those LLMs construct your queries,
then we will compile and run them, give
you your data,
and there's basically no need to use
APIs or anything. It just works like
that.
We have introduced four new system
tools.
Um you can see them here in the
configuration. When you enable the data
tool on the server features, you get a
find tables data find tables tool, you
get a
table relations tool, you get a table
schema tool, and a data query tool.
But it's so boring hearing me talking
about that when we can see a live demo.
So, Poor Shot, why why don't you show us
what you built?
>> All right.
So, first of all, the main idea with the
data tools was to enable generic data
analysis for our users. Because with the
APIs, of course, you have full control
over what APIs you have. You define them
on your configurations and you get the
data according to the APIs that you've
set up.
But with the data query tools, it
completely depends on the permissions
that you already have, the tables that
you have access to in Business Central,
and how good your agent is at writing AL
queries.
So, in my setup, what I have is I've set
up the Business Central
MCP, as you can see on the left here.
And I've also set up the Microsoft Docs
MCP, which is great for agents as well
to learn how to write good AL queries,
right?
And as an example, I asked my agent a
very simple question. I asked the agent
to get me all my customers, their
orders, and for each order also to get
the line, as well as
just to get an analysis of what is it
that people are actually buying, right?
And as you can see, it does something it
takes 30 steps, it takes 2 minutes. It's
a good example of a long-running agent.
And it comes up with a very good
analysis, right? It comes up with the
customer's summary of what the customers
are buying, the number of lines for
their orders.
And as you can see, there's also nice
observations towards the bottom that
Atlanta white boat accounts for like
46.2% of open orders. Okay.
Well, let's actually see how this works
by looking at what the agent did, right?
So, the agent starts by searching for
the Business Central tables.
And it will provide some search text and
it will get a set of tables that we have
in Business Central.
And then it starts searching in the
documentation, essentially searching for
how to write good AL queries. And as you
can see here, it starts searching for
Business Central AL query object, nested
data items, and so on.
>> So, yeah, so we are not So, just for my
understanding, so
the MCP host is not sending that user
query to our MCP server and we'll do
that, right? So
>> Exactly. Yeah, it's a additional MCP
server from Microsoft and you're free to
use it, but at the same time we have
seen that newer models are actually
pretty good at writing AL query. So,
they don't really end up using it as
much.
But then as you can see, the agent
starts exploring the different tables
that we have in Business Central. And
that's what this uh get Business Central
table schema is about, right? It will
find tables and then it will look at
what fields are actually
available on all of these tables.
Once it's done with that, it asked me a
couple of questions like what is the
time period for which I want this
analysis and what are the different
things I want this analysis to cover.
And then finally, it also looked at
table relations, essentially
understanding how is one table connected
to other tables in Business Central
because that's how you write good join
queries in Business Central, right?
Once it's done with that, it starts
writing the AL queries as you can see
here at the bottom. It will start by
compiling queries and as you can see, if
it compiles a query and it fails, the
compilation messages you get is directly
from our compiler, right? And so often
times the agent is able to correct
itself and figure out that okay, this is
a mistake I made, this is how I need to
correct myself.
And then finally, it runs the final
queries that it has compiled
and you get the output. An agent is able
to access anything. I think this is a
very powerful feature for generic data
analysis from Business Central.
>> Awesome. Super demo, Pooshat. Thank you
so much.
One a few things maybe that we should
explain here is that since this data is
based on queries,
that also means that this tool can
basically has the power of queries and
the limitations of queries.
>> Exactly.
>> So, whatever you can express in an AL
query is now available to agents. If you
have data questions that will
kind of result in a query that is not
supported in the query
>> Or even not optimal.
>> Or or not optimal, then of course that
will not work.
>> Exactly. Yeah.
There are also limitations in queries in
Business Central on how much data can be
returned and for how long the query can
run.
But I I do think that this is going to
be extremely helpful for ad hoc analysis
on where no object necessarily exists
that joins data this way.
All right, the second part of this video
is about what
the UX we did for
configurations and also a security
feature in case you want to complete
control of whether the MCP server
feature as such should be available or
not.
So here is the new UX for MCP
configurations. You can see that we have
added a new box called server features.
So we're now
trying to distinguish between server
features such as such as the data tool
and the APIs that are coming below that.
And for each of the day the server
features, we then have
the box on the right showing which tools
I which tools this particular feature
will open up for. Actually, it will be
the combination. So if you enable a
couple of server features
on the system tools box, you would see
all the tools that these server features
enable.
And then as I mentioned for the security
part, we have now a new toggle in in the
copilot and agent capabilities page
where you can
uh
activate or deactivate the MCP server as
such.
And that's it, Poojat. We just have one
more thing and that is if you want to
learn more about MCP server in general
for Business Central, we have a landing
page for you, aka.ms/bcmcp.
And with that, that ends our launch
edition video on MCP server. We hope you
will enjoy many of the other videos.
But Pourchot and I
are out.
>> Thank you.